Pavel V. Fomin

Information Technology Consultant

Location: Plymouth, MN, USA LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/pfomin Email: pfomin-resume@yahoo.com

Profile

- Over 10 years of software design and development experience in diverse industry environment
- Strong expertise in Java and JEE architecture with various Application and Web servers
- Solid RDBMS and NoSQL background

Skills Summary

Operating Systems Linux (Ubuntu, Mint, Redhat, SUSE), Unix (Solaris, AIX, SCO), Mac OS X, MS Windows

Java 1.1-11, Groovy, Bash, SQL, HTML, JavaScript, CSS Languages

Frameworks JSE/JEE: JAX-RS, JAX-WS, JDBC, JMS, JMX, EJB, JSP, JSTL, JSF, Servlets

Spring: Spring Boot 1.x/2.x, Spring Core 2/3/4/5, MVC, JDBC Template, Security, Web Services, Rest Template, AMQP, Spring

Data, Spring Data Solr

NoSQL: Riak. MongoDB Databases

Relational: Oracle 7-12c, MySQL, MS SQL Server, Sybase

Tomcat 3-9, Jetty, Liferay Portal Server 6.2, IBM Websphere Application Server 4/5/6/7, IBM Websphere Portal Server 6.1, OAS 10g, Application Servers

Resin, BEA Weblogic 4.5.1/5.1/6.1, Borland Inprise Application Server 4.x, JBoss, Apache Web Server, Oracle Web Server 2.1.1

Tools IDE: IntelliJ, Eclipse, Emacs

Methodologies Agile, SCRUM, Kanban, Test Driven Development

Industries Retail, Loyalty Management, Medical supplies, Education, Finance, Banking, E-commerce, Healthcare, Medical Software, Software

Development, Energy Management, Telematics

Work History

Aimia Loyalty Solutions, Product Engineering

Consultant 11/2019 - Present

Environment: Jetty, AWS, Docker, Linux, Mac OS X, MySQL

Tools: JDK 1.7/1.8, Kotlin, Spring Boot 2.2, Maven, Gradle, IntelliJ, Emacs, Git, Jira, Slack

Helped with technical evaluation of the Aimia Loyalty Platform code base. Created multiple POCs using Spring Boot, Java and Kotlin with the goal of separating existing code base into multiple micro services. Implemented multiple enhancements to improve system performance. Created Spring Boot based security library adding OAuth 2.0 / JWT option to the existing custom token authentication model. Developed automated functional testing suite using Groovy and Spock.

Target Corporation, Enterprise Payment Gateway

Consultant 05/2018 - 09/2019

Environment: Tomcat 9, Consul, Apache / Nginx, Kafka, VMASS, OpenStack, Docker, Linux, Mac OS X, Oracle 11 / 12

Tools: JDK 1.8 / 11, Spring Boot 1.5 / 2.1, Spring Cloud Netflix / Consul, Consul Template, Hystrix, Mayen, IntelliJ, Emacs, Git, Drone, SonarQube, Oracle VirtualBox, Grafana, ELK Stack, Jira, Slack

Led a number of technical initiatives to improve security, stability, maintainability and scalability of the Enterprise Payment Gateway technical stack. Focused on foundational engineering tasks including creation of shared Spring Boot based libraries, migration of the application security model from Basic to OAuth 2.0 / JWT authentication and authorization, transition from Netflix to Consul based cloud registration, discovery and configuration services and migration to Java 11. Helped with establishing best practices in the test driven development, build, release, deployment and provisioning automation using Git, Drone and Chef.

Solution Design Group, Professional Services

Senior Consultant

10/2014 - 05/2018

McKesson Medical-Surgical, Web Development

Environment: Tomcat 7/8, Azure, Pivotal Cloud Foundry and private VMware OneCloud platforms, Linux, Windows 7, Oracle 11g

Tools: JDK 1.8, Spring Boot 1.5, Spring 4.x, Maven, Gradle, Eclipse (Mars), Emacs, Git, Bamboo, Concourse, Oracle VirtualBox, Jira, Slack

Created several Spring Boot based micro services providing new patient, formulary, order validation and submission functionality. Used private Vmware OneCloud, Azure and Pivotal Cloud Foundry to enable application independent scalability and cloud deployment. Helped establish best practices in the test driven development, automated build and deployment processes. Completed Docker Swarm, Kubernetes and Pivotal Cloud Foundry POCs using Azure and private VMware OneCloud platforms helping with the cloud deployment strategy selection.

Best Buy. Cloud Services Development

Environment: Tomcat 7.x, Riak, Memcached, Ehcache, Amazon EC2, OpenStack, Akamai, Linux, Mac OS X

Tools: JDK 1.7 / 1.8, Spring 4.x, Groovy, Spock, IntelliJ, Emacs, Git, Maven, Gradle, Jenkins, Oracle VirtualBox, Jira

Created highly scalable aggregation and transformation services for BestBuy.com to support functionality of new business initiatives. Implemented various architectural initiatives including domain services development, service integration with Node rendering tier and responsive front end redesign using Groovy and Spring framework in Amazon EC2 and OpenStack cloud environments. Used Akamai CDN and Edge Side Includes to offload edge traffic while providing configurable cache expiration and flushing capabilities of page fragments. Utilized Memcached and Ehcache to increase performance of the services tier.

McKesson Medical-Surgical, Web Development

Environment: Liferay 6.2 EE, Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11g, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.7, Spring 4.0, Solr, Nutch, JSP, Freemarker, jQuery, Sass, Bourbon with Bitters and Neat, Maven, Eclipse (Luna), Emacs, CVS, Git, Jenkins, Jira, DynaTrace

Implemented new public web site for McKesson using Liferay 6.2 EE Portal server enabling content authors to publish changes without application code deployment. Created several Liferay portal plugins to customize the Liferay implementation for the client. Setup clustered site search using separate Solr server and Liferay Solr plugin. Used DynaTrace to identify the performance bottlenecks during the load tests.

Data Recognition Corporation, Information Services

Senior Software Developer

10/2013 - 10/2014

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, MongoDB, MySQL, MS Sql Server, OpenAM, Linux, Windows 7, Amazon EC2

Tools: JDK 1.7, Spring 3.x, SiteMesh, Groovy, Grails, Node.js, jQuery, Junit, Spock, Eclipse, Emacs, Git, GitHub, Maven, Jenkins, Vagrant, Oracle VirtualBox, Puppet, Jira

Developed new components of the IAT, the school test creation and administration tool. Created new Text To Speech implementation service using Node.js.

Object Partners, Professional Services

Senior Consultant

12/2011 - 10/2013

Menards, Web Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x (tcServer), MySQL, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, JDBC, JSP, Velocity, jQuery, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, Hibernate 3.6, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Jenkins, Redmine, CodeCollaborator

Added new features to the Menards e-commerce web site and internal web site administration tool.

PeopleNet, Backend Services Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, MySQL, MS Sql Server, Linux, Windows 7, Amazon EC2

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, RabbitMQ, 2lemetry, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Maven, Jenkins, Version One

Developed new and modified existing components of the asynchronous back-end services. Created RabbitMQ AMQP based guaranteed message delivery queuing Proof-of-Concept solution, deployed to local data center and to Amazon EC2 environment. Created facade for 2lemetry m2m rest api. Created new components for the custom load test engine to perform the load testing of the new services.

Room and Board, Web Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11, Akamai, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, JDBC, JSP, SiteMesh, Freemarker 2.3, jQuery, Memcache, Ivy, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, DbUnit 2.4, Groovy, OpenORM, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Bamboo, Crucible, Jira

Developed new and modified existing components of the web site and internal web site administration tool. Focused primarily on the controller and backend services. Helped to design and implement the data versioning feature in the database schema. Created new and enhanced existing components of the UI layer using HTML, JSP, Freemarker, JavaScript and jQuery.

MoneyGram International, Systems Development

Lead Developer (Software Engineer IV)

10/2007 - 12/2011

Environment: JEE, Websphere Application Server 7.x/6.x/5.x, Tomcat 4.x/6.x, Websphere Portal 6.1, Oracle, IBM MQ, Windows XP, Linux Tools: JDK 1.4/1.5/1.6, Spring (MVC), JSP, JSF, Portlet, Servlet, Ajax, jQuery, Wicket 1.2, Struts, JAX-WS, Axis 1.4, Ehcache 2, JDBC, XML, Ant, Log4j, JUnit, WSS4J, Castor 0.9/1.2, SoapUI, Eclipse, RAD 6/7/8, Emacs, CVS, Git, UML, Hudson, DokuWiki, Rally, XPlanner

Led the design and development of the JAX-WS based web services layer for the new Web Point of Entry system (Web POE). Created two prototypes of the new web site using JSF 2 and Spring MVC 3 frameworks. The Spring MVC based prototype became the foundation for the Web POE. Created the device authentication component using the signed java applet technology to enhance the security of the Web POE site. Demonstrated the Eclipse and Tomcat servlet container efficiency for the web development while supporting the deployment of the same code base on Websphere application server.

HSBC (former Metris Companies), Enterprise Application Management

Lead J2EE Developer (Senior Consultant, Business Systems)

07/2004 - 10/2007

Environment: J2EE, OAS 10g Portal, Websphere 6.x/5.x, Resin 2.x, Tomcat 4.x, Apache 1.3, Oracle 10g, IBM MQ, Windows XP, Linux (RedHat), AIX Tools: JDK 1.4, JSP, Servlet, Struts 1.1, Spring 2.0, Hibernate 3.0, JDBC, XML, XSLT, Ant 1.6, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Eclipse, RAD, Emacs, CVS, PVCS, MKS, Together Architect, MS Visio, UML, Optimizeit Enterprise Suite (Profiler), Bugzilla

Led the design and development effort to bring aboard a number of the business partners critical for the credit card accounts acquisition business. Created new and redesigned existing web based applications in the Internet and Intranet portal environment. Created fully automated application release and deployment management process based on Ant's templated approach and CVS. Led a number of migrations of the Internet environment from the web applications side.

Education

Novosibirsk State Technical University, Novosibirsk, Russia

M.S. in Computer Science and B.S. in Mathematics

Evaluated by International Education Evaluation, Inc. (REF # 116-0369)

Red Hat, Inc.

RH133 - System Administration, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 course, 2005

Successfully completed all Red Hat Certified Technician program requirements and is certified as a Red Hat Certified Technician, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4.

The George Washington University School of Business

Managing IT Projects course, 2006

The George Washington University School of Business

IT Risk Management course, 2007

Object Partners

Groovy and Grails, 2012

Last modified: 2020/06/18